Okay.
Hi Kabir, so how's everyone doing guys, how's your energy, we are about to complete our
HTMLC, CSSJS, we'll get started with React next week, how are you guys feeling about
that? Excited or the current content you have consumed is heavy? Panic? Why Kabir, you've
been following up classes right? Let's keep that worry aside guys, panic, worry, these
are big words, okay, yeah, so I'm planning something for that Muneshwar, so we'll talk
about it like once we have good amount of people, I wanted to take some initiative,
let's see how many people joins that or how that will go, because I want you guys to be,
if you are learning, since when we say it's a full stack developer, it's more of a front-end
full stack developer isn't it, so the more knowledge is consumed on the browser side,
so considering that, I want everyone to be good with that web development part at least,
so let's see, I'll talk about that in some time, but keep that worry aside guys, someone
thinking like where to start, I'll talk about that Kabir, so can I attend, yeah somebody,
you can attend, you can attend, yeah, yeah Kabir, you can ask, you can ask, we have good
amount of time, we can ask, so okay, so let me open VS code, yeah, I'll repeat that Arun,
I'll repeat that before getting started with today's class, we'll again solve last 4 to 5
questions, so that everyone is you know fresh with that energy, but let me take up a question
by Kabir, so he had some question, okay, let's do one thing, I'll paste your question here,
post end of the class, let me know if you are able to answer this or not, okay, I won't pick it up
right away, because this concept will be covered today, okay, works Kabir, I'll add your question
as doubt, so let me start the screen share guys, do let me know if you can see the screen share,
guys can you see the screen share, working fine, cool, so I've seen right, I've taken a poll related
to assignments first, so I wanted to talk more on that, like I want to talk about whole about
curriculum part, like how things spin, how we can improve on, so from your point of view,
from my point of view or scalar point of view, right, so there are too many things that we have
to discuss and we will sit together with your points with my points, right, so let's communicate
that way, then it will be better for us, okay, I see only 19 people, let's say I put
a message,
okay, I see two people joined more, but let's wait for three to four minutes more, before
we talk on anything else, but anyone having any particular like, you know, anything that if you
concerns, please do let me know, okay, I don't see any concern, specifically anyone having it,
but if you have anything, you can ping me personally and you know, set up the meeting with me,
we can discuss over it, since you know, one thing that I want to tell you is like after Thursday's
class, we have Friday, Saturday and Sunday, three days, where you might be taking a contest on this,
and this contest will be specifically based on from async classes, async classes to post,
but I want all of you to be, you know, thorough with all the concepts that we have learned,
I'll talk about it, how we can achieve that, how we can prepare for that, but again, I don't see
people coming up, Abhinav, I'll make sure that you have all the content, so even if it is not
there, you can ask me anytime, anything, but everything will be covered, okay, so if you know
all these basics in a right fashion, right way, those things will be pretty easy,
okay, can we fetch data from excel, surely upendra, you can read it from excel or any type
of data type, any MIME type right, like you can read data from that, it would be interesting,
it would be kind of reverse engineering Abhinav for you, so let's see, like when we see 12 classes,
it's approximately one month, if I don't have any emergencies, it will be done in one month, so
you can say mid of April, by April you should be having good amount of knowledge, and with you,
Abhinav having hands-on, it would be far easier for you, better like day to day and day out,
because you'll be having a really good code base already available to you to understand the code,
read through the code, right, I hope that's a latest code, right, it's having all functional
components, like if you understand that keyword at least, there are no classes in that, yeah, okay,
great,
great upendra, so I hope everyone is, you know, trying to apply the knowledge we have gained
over the time, just try to put your hands through, as I told you, it's when you're being a UI
developer or front-end developer, it's all about visualization, how do you see things working,
where things should be going, what, how it should be working, so the more curious you are understanding
the real-time world, like whatever you see on screens or the desktop, even for the matter, say
televisions or any screens that you see, you should be able to see like what it takes to build that,
how would you do it, okay, that initial state of my initial state should be clear, that picture
should be clear in your understanding, how you can do it, okay, so I see that, you know, it's 10
minutes, but let me pull the screen,
okay, so can we get started guys, it's 10 minutes up, with one thumbs up, I have good amount of
people, I expect everyone to be active today, so please guys, keep reacting it, keep showing
like, you know, that you are excited about things, like how things are going to be, so
there are two classes left specifically for completing whole HTML, CSS and JS part,
these are three introductory modules,
okay, so you have already completed two contexts, so I hope everyone has already attempted it,
guys can you give a thumbs up, if you have attended already two contests that has been taken place,
and I also assume people who are giving me thumbs up, they also felt that those topics are really
relatable, right, every topic, so I mean, you would have that, you would completely understand
it, you know, that's my, keep trust on me, will help you out, okay, so now there is a one more
contest coming up guys, which will be based on mostly on the JS part, so be ready with that,
and don't be worried or panic or wait to start, how to start, what to ready, because after this
contest, we are going to have a mock interview, which is more important, from people, is there
anyone who picked up masters here, it's Kayla, is there anyone who picked up masters,
I don't see, I have seen only one people giving me thumbs up too,
okay, is it recording,
is my screen share visible guys,
Maneshwara says that I don't see a timer, which I usually I can see,
hey, it's working fine, it's not, I cannot talk on that, we know, it's really helpful,
if you are not from CS background, but it's also like anyways, you are putting all amount of
efforts going through the curriculum, it's just like giving a few more exams and you get a degree,
why not, right, that's another reason, and plus, it really helps you, if you are planning to migrate
to Europe in future, if you have an European credits, it's really easy for you, right,
showing that I've studied here, so so and so, your immigration becomes easy, so there are multiple
benefits out of it, multiple things, so you have to consider that, so you can reach out any help
desk, but I see that there are two people who are actually attempting taking the masters,
right, yeah, it is an European degree, it is not an Indian degree, so the credits will be ECTS
credits, so this this credit system is based out of Europe, so the degree is only valid in Europe,
and whichever country accepts the ECTS, ECTS credits, those countries also agree that you
have done the masters, so basically Europe's a Europe centric and North America, South America,
everyone agrees that you have done masters or proper masters, so it's a valid kind of thing,
so but one thing I want to mention about mock is that, it's one is like people who are doing
masters, and people who are not even doing masters, but you know, if you have gone through
placement policies, one of the most important thing, if they want to shortlist, if scaler need
to help you out, they always check whether the mock interview is cleared or not, let's say you in
your resume, you say that you have mentioned HTML, CSS, JS, right, you mentioned three of them,
but they'll check whether this person is qualified, like when how they filter it out,
is that depending on your mock clearance, your resume, you are like, you cannot apply it, most
of the things on your career portal, from a scaler's help, the second thing is, and the
con mocks are not really in order to judge you, not in order to judge you, but in order to help
you out, actually, if you think from the perspective of taking a hell, it would be really working in
your case, because you have multiple attempts, you can do it, and this, whatever we are learning,
monstack, the basic building block for this one, we have covered most of them, like these three
concepts, so I hope once you are better clear with this, and you clear mocks, you'll be better
equipped, understanding react and node.js, and which will boost you up whenever you go and face
interviews, so I wouldn't prefer anyone, like once we complete react classes, directly go and sit in
interviews, just go and give a mock, try to see what actually the people who are in industry already,
what they expect out of you, when you say that I'm a react developer or I'm a front end developer,
so check like whether they're asking machine coding or theory questions, there is nothing
costing you, you have already paid fees for that, it's just that if you give an attempt, you get to
know it more, okay, so please remove these two words, like panic and worry, this doesn't really
help, okay, not a worth of it, like be chill, enjoy the journey, firstly, enjoy the process,
go through the content, I have given you all the github codes, I've always been available, whoever
asked me out, like I've been always like first to react it, or help them out, so if you need any
help, I'll be there, so there's one more initiative that I'm taking for you all guys is that,
so I've seen when I've raised poll, let's say if there are 100% of people who reacted to that poll
in whatsapp, if you see more than 50% of people are above 80% of PSP in PSP terms, and there are
30% of people above 50,
right, and 20% of people below 50, so my target firstly, in order to revise concepts,
how would you revise any concept, how would you do it anything faster, because R in HTML, CSS, JS,
all things are mostly theory, even if you go for assignments or homework problems, most of them
were theory, so what I want is that you revising the stuff firstly, revising assignment questions,
which in turn, which will help you, hey, this is a concept and let's figure out, reattempting it,
okay, people who have done, I really appreciate your effort, but I want all the other people also,
join in, try to complete it, and revising through assignments would be far easier than
going through each of the notes, do you guys agree with that point, because after each class,
you might have 5 to 10 questions, and it would be really easy to skim through it, like one by one,
and if you do it twice, let's say you pick it up, let's say you pick it up HTML, like for one hour,
it has only two classes, it will take more than enough one hour, CSS, let's say you give three
hours, right, it has five classes, that's done, two topics are done, JS, maybe split into three parts,
async.js, then you have DOM manipulation, where you actually interact with it, then you have the
other important concepts like harvesting and any other important concepts that you think of, so
split one by one, and divide into hours, and so that you can, you know, everything, if you see a
really big picture, that here I have too much of syllabus, and covering that one would be really
difficult for me, don't think it that way, take it part by part, as we have covered the classes,
where like 30 classes of content revision may not be done in one hour, it may not be done in two
hours, for the complete beginner, it might take 10 hours, that's okay, it's all fine, we have assigned,
we've been, you know, taken up this challenge itself, where we'll try to complete that,
and be good with that, so break your task, whichever task you have, into multiple small
chunks, and try to go through it, and I'm going to be with you, so what I thought is right,
one initiative to help you out guys, to achieve, you know, completing, so I just, you know,
my goal, since first thing is like everyone have, everyone have paid, everyone have paid that same
amount of money, right, so everyone had paid same amount of money, so I just want everyone to have
this 100% firstly on this, 100% of PSP, which will help me out, ensure that whatever I deliver in
React and Node.js, you are able to understand that firstly, if you know, if you go and check that,
a share that I have done in WhatsApp group, that one particular LinkedIn post, have 90% of concepts
we have, you know, revised in JS part, I mean, discussed in JS part, so five to six files,
which will cover most of them, if you skim through it, the topics will be covered, so I've
wantedly shared that, where you can start that particular, you know, a LinkedIn post, which has
a multiple, everyone can look at it in WhatsApp group, so maybe I'll share that and I'll show it,
yeah, do check that, but it will cover, so the initiative that I was talking about is that, you
know, one thing usually you might have been saved from the day one class that, hey, if your class is
from 9 to 11.30 pm on Tuesday, Thursday, Saturday, don't consider the other days as holiday, like
Monday, Wednesday and Friday, like try to spend this two hours, two and a half hours, right,
this might have been already told to you, that leverage this other days,
you know, are you able to do that, are you actually consciously able to do that,
did anyone try, are you able to leverage this, the other alternate days, so this is where I
wanted to take initiative, so one thing I thought was like, where I can, because I've seen people
having reasons that, hey, I have office, I have class, I have home and multiple other responsibilities,
all right, that's all fine, in my case, I have office, I have class, I have to prep for class
and home, do you see that I have an extra work than you guys,
can you consider that I have to prep for it, for your class, like if I want to teach you,
I have to be preparing that content, isn't it, so I have some extra work more than you, so even then
like what I'm planning is like, I'll sit with you, along with you on this Monday, Wednesday, Friday,
where we'll be, you know, on session, like where you can group of people can come and join, it's
like a kind of a study, where we won't be talking much, but I just want to show that, how can you
manage time better, I'll be sitting with you, on back of site, either you do office work, either
you do your assignments, either you do something, we can keep communicating, we can keep chatting,
but I just want you to spend those like 9 to 11.30, blocking those hours, right, I want to block
these hours for the next two months, because the important topics are going to come up and
everything will be, you know, bundled up together and it would be difficult for you to digest it,
so do you guys want to do that,
yeah, Abhinav says that he is doing actually, you know, assignments in the free time itself,
so Abhinav, you can do that in session, like you can do other office work again, or like you can
study about the like mock interview, so anything you can do, I'll be there, we can chat, we can
discuss about a certain topic, if you have, so I just want to make sure that I'm with you guys,
like it's like a kind of a you can say, if you have a face somewhere like study or concept,
where I'll be doing my own personal work, maybe my office work or anything, but I'll be there
with you guys, okay, so I tried to find multiple mediums, like maybe google meet, zoom calls,
right, nothing was working out, because everything has its own limitations, when you consider like
how many people can join, how long you will have it, so even, you know, creating a dummy class would
be really difficult, like in scalar also, so I thought that like I'll be streaming on youtube,
where we can discuss it, I'll share personal link with you in the whatsapp group, where you can join
and we can discuss over, because these people provide free services, right, everyone keeps
streaming it, so we'll use it for studies, like parallelly, so I hope you sign up, because I'm
here to help you out and you have signed up to take up this big task, where you are actually
paying this too much amount of money, where you want to leverage it, so let's come back,
let's stick together, let's figure out what we need to do and how we want to approach,
right, so first and foremost thing, I, yeah, so Muneshwara says that this has already happened,
okay, discord server, I'll check that, so I'll do that, but I just created a youtube account,
so I just thought like I didn't find anything, but even we can do the discord server, but what
I'll do is that, once we pass out, right, I'll create a discord server, where we can keep
communicating offline, anyways we have whatsapp, I'll be anyways available to you all guys,
but let's see, let's start that initiative, I just want that people come in and leverage this two
and a half hours and only my efforts are towards your betterment, where you try to achieve this
mark and you know, if I see some people, while the batch is going on, if one two people even get
placed from react or node.js, it would be really good for me, like if I just want to know your
experiences, how things are going, even for the mock attempt, right, so I'm going to do that,
so that's the reason why I'm trying to push you guys, and only this way you will be able
to study and revise the concepts too, and I'll be available, so that you go through
the github nodes, anything, if they're like you can revise it and come back to me, so does it
does it find good guys, would you be joining it, give me thumbs up, if you feeling like joining it,
so I'll be pasting that links in the alternate days of class, in the like whatsapp group,
I hope to see everyone, who are you know, wanted to actually build their thing, I'm not asking you
to particularly drive any particular task, that you do it, it's your forum, you do it anything,
but I'm there with you, if you need anything from my side, okay, it's just that we are doing
collectively sitting and doing our own works, okay, so that's it for today, I hope you guys
okay, so I just want this to you know, you guys clear mock interviews and prep for that, okay,
so with this, that was a short announcement that I wanted to do, but let's get started with
today's agenda, what we are going to discuss, and how today's class is going to be, so mostly right,
we have two classes, so I'll try to cover today closure, and do you know we have missed two data
searches, like in JS, a good amount of like important data, like when we cover data types
and other things, do you think anything we have missed it, does anyone recall that something we
haven't covered, do you remember have we covered map and set, do you recall if we came across this
use case, no right, so we'll cover these three things today, from like you know, like we'll
just put our hands to understand the concepts, in the next class,
right, next class is more of a advanced asynchronous coding, where there is nothing like
a more advanced asynchronous coding, but what I'll do is that, since we have two and a half hours,
I'll try to revise whole things that we have done it till now, whoever are not attempted any class
or didn't come across, I would ask everyone to be there, and I would ask you to nominate
like which topic you want to re-discuss on the WhatsApp group, or if you want to pick it up
something new, ping that nominate that topic, so that we revise through the things and understand
it completely digested, and one more thing I have shared you one of the, yeah we'll do that poll
Kabir, we'll do that poll, but I've shared you one of the document, like how does web works,
how many of you have read that, like I mean, like how HTML, CSS and JS is rendered into browser,
yeah, we'll be doing that anyways some bit in the future, so I just want to cover the whole
in the future, so I just want to cover the concepts that we have done it, so we'll pick
it up that way, but guys have you read this something like a document that I've shared you,
like how actually it's done, how these three things work together and build, okay,
so I'll pick it up first this one, which actually shows you in behind the scenes how things works,
so one topic will be covered,
okay great, so other can nominate it, but let's start with some of the coding guys for today,
firstly then we'll come to closure and everything, understanding those topics,
let's say I call it as, firstly let me create an index.html file, I hope you can see
Visual Studio code, right, okay, let's say you have script,
okay, so
now, so I have few questions for you again, okay, before starting today's content, I just want to
revise few things that I have done in previous class, how many of you were there in previous
class guys, give me thumbs up, if there is anyone who was not there, I see only one thumbs down,
okay,
but let's say if I go back to the previous class and I've covered good amount of examples here,
okay, just let's just try to you know revise few of the things, how these things were working,
okay, I'll try to remove all the answers that I have, will revise few examples,
like how we were able to get this and what was the concept behind, okay,
let's say we start from 18, yes, I just want you to recall or you know, what do you think
the answer for this one would be, firstly, I just want someone to you know think what would be the
output for this one, for the parent file, just think of this one guys, for five minutes, because
the topic is dependent on this, if you have the good understanding of this, things are sorted,
though we have done in last class, have received really great amount of answers,
but just rechecking this one,
I hope everyone is again trying to solve this,
Muneshwara has given an answer, but any other people are trying it again,
okay, Arun has given an answer, so there's a difference in answers now,
okay, just keep adding your answers again, Thiraj has given his answer,
guys, I need some new names who are trying out, because Shambhu, okay, you have given an answer,
any other one, few more, three to four, people giving me this answer would be really great,
so I hope everyone is paying attention, this concept is really important and
you will be seeing day in day out, every day in your code, whichever code you write in JS,
you will be seeing these concepts again and again, okay, Kishore has given his answer,
so with this, let's see this again, guys, what just happened, yeah, so
now as soon as first call is like, we call the parent file and this is something in parent file,
these three things are there, so firstly, we have a var variable, a equal to 20, which is hoisted,
initialized with undefined, sorry, declared with initially initialized with undefined, then
actual initialization happens, where 20 is assigned to this a variable, right, then you have a function
definition, but here you are calling that function, so once your code execution comes here, it goes
inside this child function, now let's see what is happening in child function, now here, if you see,
there is a new memory of a is created, okay, whenever you see firstly, a new variable is
created, this is actually every, we know that every function executes in a separate execution
context and by default, each function have its, you know, the scope of parent,
the global execution context, it is available through lexical scoping, right, scope chain,
there's a level of scopes, different scope, so you always, your child functions or the functions
which are inside of functions, always have an access to previous, right, that's through happening
through lexical scoping, now once we have it here, we see that there's a new value, it's initialized,
now in this particular execution context, another a variable is initialized, this is not going to
update this existing var, okay, now let us initialize with 10 and we're trying to output
the console log of a, now this will check this firstly a, whether in its current local memory,
a value a is available, it says that it is available, then it will print that then, now
this function declaration comes, then we call that function, now it goes inside that function,
now we are trying to directly print it, it checks whether in its memory, any there is a new creation
of variable with variable a, there is no variable a available here, right, then it goes to the parent
level scope which is its lexical scope, here it sees that let a is 10 is available in parent scope,
immediate parent, okay, then 10 is printed, then we are actually updating a equal to 30
and that 30 is actually updating this value as a equal to 30, right, now whenever
this value is actually updated and you come out, this child like two is executed and you see there
is a console log of a, now if you see the value of a is updated as 30 in its scope, it prints 30,
then once if we minimize this child, this whole execution is completed, it comes to the last point
again it sees a equal to 20, right, so the answer comes 10 10 30 20,
right, I hope everyone is clear with this point, is this anyone Arun, is this clear with you,
okay, I hope this is clear with you, now let's go back up, let's answer this one, the parent 4,
okay, the parent 4, once again,
okay,
guys, I hope you are trying it out, some patience for some time would be really helpful,
just a revision of concepts where you think in terms of execution context,
plus hoisting, plus how things are working, right, so Maneshwara has given his answer,
I need at least five to six answers from different people, so that I can re-explain that,
got two answers,
three,
four,
great, I got five answers, so somebody has, okay, great guys, great, great effort, so I've received
good amount of answers, so let's revise this again, so firstly, function, let's say this
parent 4, okay, so initially it sees function, it hoist that function, then function call is
actually happening, it goes inside this function, our new execution context for parent 4 is created,
with having access to the global scope, with this keyword, in this new execution context,
inside this execution, new created execution context for parent 4, a variable is declared,
which is hoisted with undefined, then initialized with 20, it goes to the function firstly at line
number 165 to execute it, it enters into the child function, once it enters, it sees a new
variable again, in its new execution context for the child, so let a equal to 10, now whenever we
are trying to console log in a, so firstly it will try to access here itself, since a is available
in its own scope, okay, let's say I print a, then I create, this function is hoisted and kept ready,
then you go and see that there's another console log of a, so it will print again a 10, then you
see that hey I'm calling this child to function, so I'll go inside this function, I'll see another
console log of a, since in this scope there is no a available, it will go to the parent scope,
which is its lexical scope, it sees that a value a equal to 10, so it will take 10, then we are
trying to actually update a equal to 30, which is updating this one, let a equal to 30, right, now
whenever you come outside, let's say when this a is actually updated as 30,
right, now let's say this execution of child function is done, now once the execution of
child is done, it comes to the next line, it sees that what is the value of a in parent's scope,
so we see that 20, okay, so it's 10, 10, 10, 20, I hope I have got 100% right answers and I hope
everyone is also aligned with this, okay, let me solve this functions parent tree directly, okay,
so firstly we call a parent tree function, we go inside this function and value a is initialized
with a equal to 20, then you see that child is being called, so you go inside the child function
and you see a console log of a, since here there is no variable is initialized, we see there is no
variable installed in the child, so it will try to access from the parent, which it will receive it
as 20, then it sees that hey when I try to update here a equal to 10, actually I'm updating here a
equal to 10, right, once I update it here, then I'm calling child two, let's say if I go into the
child two and I try to print console log of a, it should print 10, because it is updated in its
parent scope, parent's lexical scope, then but if you see here it shouldn't be coming as 10,
reason behind in this scope variable a is already initialized, isn't it, new variable is created in
its local scope and whenever we see a variable initialized with var keyword, those are generally
hoisted and set with undefined, now first it will check in its local scope, does variable a exist,
it says that variable a exists, but the value is undefined whenever you try to do console log,
because initialized doesn't went through this scope, okay, now this line get executed,
value is updated as 30 for this particular scope, now this child to execution is done,
then you come back, a child is also done, you come back here, you check that hey value of a equal to 10,
so you update this, is this clear guys, I hope everyone is aligned with this answer also,
right, now, so now do you understand the lexical scoping,
a one second child, okay, let's see this what happened here, now if you see once we have
144 is executed Kabir, we updated var equal to 10, because in this particular scope,
in the child scope, we don't have variable initialized or created in a local memory,
so it goes and check whether it is not there in my space, so it will check in the parent,
so it checks in the parent updates at 10, okay, then child to get executed, when you go into the
child to, if you see first hoisting happens, whenever the execution context is created,
so when the when hoisting happens, variable a is actually hoisted and initialized with undefined
value and when it does happen, it starts execution, when it starts execution, it sees that there is a
console log of a and this in this execution context, it checks that whether in my local
memory, value a is already available, so it says that yeah, value a is available because we
hoisted it, now, so we'll get an since this line initialization doesn't happen with 30,
we get undefined here, okay, so now just rechecking with this, again, let me show you the
definition of lexical scope or scope chain, two things, scope chain in JavaScript and
okay, let's let's pick some article, good article, let's say, I don't want to go into
close here yet, but let's say I pick it up this one, but I hope you got the basic understanding
about scope chain, like a function is having access to the top level function, like
let's say there's an image added by in this article, so I try to zoom it in,
now, if you see here, maybe in this article, generally, whatever I'm saying is that whenever
your inner most child is actually having an access to the parent element till its global
scope, that is itself is called a scope chain from immediate parent to the upper parent, like
inheritance concept, right, having like always access to those things levels and similarly,
this concept is also called as, you know, lexical scoping,
both the things are actually meant in same way,
you see, again, this definition itself,
data success that stores a variable and functions that are defined in current scope
and all of outer scope, right, let's say, whatever the outer scope it is present,
it tries to remember all those things and along with its current scope, so bundled together,
current scope plus for our parents code is called as a lexical, you know, lexical scope,
like whatever, in general, this is also called a scope chain, you can resemble two things in
a same way, because they look both same, like you're trying to have access to all the levels,
lexical scopes also tries to state that thing itself, like current scope
plus all the levels of like access to all the variables. I hope these two points are clear,
lexical scope and scope chain,
give me thumbs up if these points are clear, what is lexical scope
and if there is anyone who don't understand it, give me thumbs down right away,
we can explore further examples and figure it out, okay, I see one thumbs down,
cool, two people, there is anyone else who don't understand it, happy to repeat it,
okay, I see two people Kabir and Rajni, now if you see this guys, what just happened here firstly,
whenever we were going inside the child, let's say child two, if you remember this a is actually
referring to the parent scope, elect a equal to 10, isn't it, do I agree with that, it is actually
trying to reach out the parent, so what I'm trying to say is that, this along the scope,
whatever in child two things are defined, along the variables and functions defined in the child
two, along with that and the all outer elements in the memory, you know, this may be the scope of
child or the parent for everything are bundled together, the memory or values available in those
bundled together is called as lexical scope, this is point clear, in general like whatever
hierarchy and this is also called as a scope chain, because like this is particularly having
an access to this one, then this one, this chain continues till the global execution context,
is this point clear guys, I hope Rajni and
right, okay, cool, now let's get started with one of the question guys, I just want to ask you one
of the question is that, let's say if I want to say that I want to build a counter,
where if I call that counter again and again, it should start printing me one, two, three,
four, say if I write down a question, let's say, implement a counter
function, that returns
plus one value, so how it would be like, let's say if there is a function that you have defined,
I'll call that counter function,
let's say I call this function, it should print one, then again if I call that counter function,
then again if I call that counter function, it should print two,
then again if I call this counter function, it should print three,
so how would you approach this question guys, how would you approach like if I want to do this
sort of implementation, it's a very basic thing, but how would you approach it,
after printing, increment the value inside the function, can anyone write down that logic for me,
can you build a function counter, can you guys take your time and write down that function counter,
so I'll be waiting for your outputs guys, just think of it, how would you build this one,
I have to execute, whenever I'm executing, actually the one should print, then two should
print, then three should print, let's say I write down a basic syntax for you,
function counter, then I have something like this, then let's say it returns something,
it returns some value here, so I've seen some bit tripartis answer, like this is where a equal to
zero console of a plus plus, okay cool, now then I have other answer, I've been of says loop,
I've been, why would I call loop, like I'm calling a function here, first think of this thing,
okay Arun says set timeout, we don't need any delay as of now, Arun just I want to add numbers,
counter, just simple counter,
just I hope you guys are thinking about it, like I just need to return, like let's say as Sambit
says that, I try to console log a value, let's say this is a val, I have to console log each time,
now firstly when I first call the function counter val, it should print this val as one,
then it should print val as two, then it should print val as three, how would you do it,
so
guys anyone trying it, is anyone attempting it,
I don't see any reactions, give me reactions at least if you are trying it out,
do you want me to do it guys,
okay I see one thumbs up that you want me to do it, but any other people,
okay, someone is asking please do it, so let's let's do this guys, now let's say if you see
firstly, I have to call this val label a value, try to print out right val, now where how can I
create a val, let's say if I create a val here, let a val equal to zero and let's say I say that
hey after console logging, increase this val plus equal to one, do you think it should work,
do you think it should work, if I do it this way,
now let's let's do this, let's do this what happening here, let's see this what happens,
okay if I try to open here a terminal and I try to do node script dot js, now do you see this,
I'm printing consistently zero firstly, any idea how can I fix this,
recursive function says Krishna, now this is a basic example, easy example,
can you guys think like how can I do it, counter val, so he promote this thing pass the value
from the like you know when you're calling the function, I don't want to do it,
if I pass value then how would I get the counter, I just want to hey whenever I come to you,
let's say Pramod I'm coming to you, I will say that hey give me the count,
you should be giving me, I don't want to give you the value, if I give you the value,
just print it, isn't it,
so chances let's define the value let outside the function,
do you guys think this should work, if I initialize with one,
guys I've received good amount of answers, now do you think the output should be right,
we're getting one two three, now but let me know, let me know this thing, now is this way of writing
logic is good, because now let's say there are n number of functions you can write in a one
JavaScript file and there might be people who want to use this I mean variable again and what
if if there is someone changing unknowingly in their logic behind the scenes and it will affect
our counter right, it's like let's say you're standing somewhere and you are trying to count
number of people coming inside and someone can just keep disturbing you or else you your focus
will be lost isn't it, so there's there is a way that someone can and reuse the value and update
the value, so we have to protect this one right, the way of protecting now how can you do it if
you're thinking from object oriented programming, what type of variable you need to declare such
that no other person from the outer scope can act you know disturb it, private isn't it, now if
we can create a private variable sort of concept where no one can come and change it right, our
problem would be solved isn't it, firstly and it would be a better way of writing code isn't it
and when I told you earlier that there is no way of syntax earlier like before ES6 right,
writing or declaring a private variable or making construct a private how there is always a way
where how you can restrict it because every language has figured out to do that same activity
now the one of the way is one of the best way is actually closures itself
in order to make any variables private or do something the answer is closure now I've
and if I tell you that you've been playing around with first class of js with from with closures
you wouldn't you've been actually using use const instead of well okay even if I use const the
I can can I update it here Pradeep can I update it here no right so my work wouldn't be done right
so no but if I if I guys if I tell you that you've been actually using closures from the day one
you would be amazed it because closures are so much near way and everywhere in the JavaScript
we'll figure it out how this is actually being done let's say if I implement this using a closure
now firstly what closure says is that now let's say that if I copy definition if I copy definition
anywhere from the internet closures in JavaScript let's say if I pick this
and go to any website let's say if we go for MDN docs any docs right let's say if I go hit here
okay now it says that let's say I copy this firstly
these two lines that's enough let's say I comment it here
so
now firstly we'll read this sentence again coming back to it later but now let's say if I want to
create if I want to solve this problem such that I make a variable private such that no one will
be able to access yeah Sasha it's kind of a function inside in a function but let's see how
do you do it let's say I have a function called create counter okay once I have a create counter
inside this I'll return a function firstly
now this syntax we have seen n number of times when as a white printed 000 last time okay what
I did is like I had this value here and I initialize it with zero now
whenever whenever I call this function let's say if I call once the value is initialized
let let is initial I mean value is initialized with zero and it tries to print zero right Arun
then you are trying to increase it but this function execution context is closed
but again you are calling a function then again it is in stress with zero
and it will be loaded again so everything happens so the execution context right you
I hope you remember that diagram memory creation and code execution face
okay I hope this doubt is solved right okay going ahead now so I hope you guys have seen
this syntax case where we try to function returning a function or function accepting
a function what what type of function is this what we call it as create counter which type
of function is this is it a higher order function guys I hope you remember that name
right it's a higher order function now let's say what I'm trying to do it here
I'll try to do the same logic let's say I copy and paste whatever I've done it here I'll paste
it here firstly now once I'm pasting it here and let's say I have to initialize it earlier
I was initializing it globally now what I'll do it here is that I'll initialize here
okay now let's see if we are able to if we are able to replicate this one firstly
okay let's say if I'm trying to able to replicate this is working fine okay
let's say I go into terminal and I try to clear it then I try to implement it now
okay so firstly it is returning a function so let's call it again
okay now if you see each time I'm calling a function so I have to store this let's say
firstly I'll show you how you can use this let's say this is a const counter one
then you can say counter one call it multiple times
okay now let's say I remove this two things as of now clear it and then execute it but both the
use cases we are able to solve this function that we are able to actually print one two three the
number of times you'll call this counter on the one it will it will give us the right value
firstly so I hope this firstly how the output is fine right I'll come to the logic how it is
working why it is working what actually happened it will figure it out step by step okay now
let's go back to the definition of closure what it is saying so a closure is a combination of
a function bundled together enclosed with reference to the surrounding state the lexical
environment okay so it says that of combination of function bundle together so if you see this
function is actually bundled together along with its lexical scope
do you see this a function bundled together along with the lexical scope this is happening here
isn't it so this thing will you know form a closure but we'll see in browser I'll show you
how this forms in other words closure gives you access to the outer function scope from
a inner function okay if you see each time I'm calling it I am getting the value
and where I'm getting this value from I'm getting a value from here
so this particular function always remembers the value or the its scope its lexical scope
it always remember its lexical scope wherever it is present even though we have returned this
function outside it was returned in the counter one right we stored that function in the counter
one even then even if you are calling it it is remembering that hey this function is actually
declared here and in spare and scope there is a value a and it doesn't actually point to the
value it actually points to the reference of the value that's the reason why when I'm calling it
first time it is regiving me one then it was actually incrementing it one by one
is is this point anyways relatable guys is anyone got this point
just rechecking with you did you understand what so now if we try to print value yeah if
we try to print value we'll always get one two three if you see let's say if I comment this one
I am not printing anything from the top counter if I'm printing it here
you see I'm able to print one two three using this counter one
so this is actually having an access to this one and this function is actually forming closure with
its this function is actually you know bundled along with its lexical scope these two things
are there now let me show you in the actually browser how this thing works
uh let's say I launch this index.html open in live server
let's say I have this I go to sources I go to the script now let's say I have here I have this
counter one let me refresh it now here if you see whenever I'm here inside it I go print now
now if you see the firstly the counter one okay the counter one is actually this particular
function isn't it this particular function where now if you are if you see that we got a call here
now if I try to click a play it will come inside this one and this particular function if you see
here I got a word called closer and the closure is actually create counter now the create counter
now the create counter is actually forming a closure and if you see if you remember the
definition which we just said that a closure is a combination of a function which is bundled
together along with its surrounding state okay the surrounding state is actual lexical environment
okay a function which is bundled together along with its function its surrounding state
so this create counter is actually forming a closure now the only thing that specialty
of closures is that it always remembers the value remembers the value of the variables the lexical
scope it doesn't actually point to the value but it points to the references okay since if why do
I'm saying that it is pointing to the references is that once this function is executed again when
we call this well it is actually updated the value is updated as two but when I'm calling
it again it is reading as a two not as a one again because it is actually pointing to value
not to the value is this clear guys how this counter is working how many of you understood
this explanation closure it's just a simple thing it's just a simple thing it's a combination of
function bundled together well along with the surrounding state
yeah like if you if you call this let's say if you call this as create counter
let's say if I call it as a create counter and that's how I call it as this one now what is our
expected output here this should be printing kabir one right if I write if here it should be
printing one then two then three again if I call this again I call this separately it should be
printing one isn't it so everything should have its own scope right everything should have its
own scope in execution context let's see if this is working fine as expected now if I execute it
if you see for the first counter whenever I created this okay I've got as a one two three
and this variable become private here because nobody will be able to access it
and nobody will be able to change it this is present inside the create counter in
in that memory execution isn't it even if you declare 100 methods below you won't be able to
change it is our problem statement solved guys
like we made a variable private so that no one can get affected and it's not publicly available
to everyone like this valve you cannot access it like outside here well it is only available
here right this definition is clear like in a closure gives you access to the outer function
scope from a inner function like this is like this function is actually having an
access to this variable that is it is talking about that but now if I tell you this
have you seen a closure example before like
can you think from this understanding have we discussed anytime closure earlier
have you came across this one point anywhere where
where you are passing a function inside then it is actually executing later on stages
even even in kanban board but really common use cases promises works in closures but guys
if you see dom events right if you go for any dom event
now this particular thing this callback function you are not actually executing it right this is
actually given to an add event listener function and doesn't know that how add event listener is
working isn't it whenever you are passing a callback inside it right we don't know how it is
actually working where this event is coming from where do you think this event is coming from
who is giving us this event we just pass it on inside this variable
if you go and see add event listener how this is returned
but in general this listeners add event listeners or to say so that bind function if you remember
that bind function that we have discussed call bind apply that bind function also forms a closure
right because that bind function is actually returning you
where is this call
okay if you remember in the bind function we were actually getting a function right output
code if you remember this bind is actually returning us that function we were executing
later stages but this reusable code is actually remembering all the information available
like if you go inside the get info get info there might be n number of things available here
and that it will remember it right i mean not
get info but inside the bind where you're passing this information
like if you go for polyfill and see how did we write it
do you see it here we are actually returning a function with all the scope in bind function
now is this my bind is a forming a closure because it is actually bundled together with a function
and along with its lexical scope isn't it this definition is still applicable here isn't it guys
do you guys agree with that point firstly whether this point is like actually we are forming a
closure here
guys how many of you are able to follow follow this point okay because here if you see this
function is being returned and will be executed and anytime that it wants but out of that it
remembers the context value any number of times you call this function it remembers the context
value and whatever changes made the context will remember it okay now let me take a one classical
example to show you let's say i have a for loop okay and this is actually how a closure is thought
in if you go anywhere let's say i have this and let's say i have this set timeout
and what i'll try to do is that i'll try to print console log
log of i now i'll try to print i every second
now what do you think the output should be here when i try to do this
just this for loop
okay guys please think of it
what do you think the output should be for this one
uh zero to ten infinite loop why do you say so muneshwar i just want to
understand interesting answer same as zero to ten okay guys any other answers anyone having
any other answers zero says eleven zero to nine
now receive different answers zero to ten zero to ten times
uh eleven zero to nine any other answers anyone having any other answers
okay let's let's see this what actually happens now do you see this actually it is printing
now so it is printing ten to sprinting ten ten number of times
now can anyone think of this thing why what what the hell has happened just like can anyone
think of this thing why this has happened what can be the reason
happened what can be the reason
but where is there but what is the problem what is an issue with the
value
can i use where and solve this issue
guys how many of you think that this answer is odd firstly like i'm just trying to print a for loop
and i'm trying to console log it should be printing the value of i from zero to nine isn't it
right so we see that 10 is actually being printed but any any idea like why this is actually happening
okay so let's say i firstly call one i go through iteration and i call the set time out and i put
it into the web api's then again a call can be done right i it is in the callback queue
okay so let's say i first call one i go through iteration and i call the set time out and i put
into the web api's then again a call can be done right i this is a like you know keep on going
right the value of i how this is actually being referred to this variables is the question
i know that it is in callback queue it comes after the one second it executing we know that
it is taking the same amount of time like if you see this i try to execute it again
it is taking time three seconds four seconds five seconds and then it is printing one by one
right so it is coming out of callback queue and coming back but when it is coming back into the
stack why the value of i available to it is becoming 10 do you see it here that actually
i is actually not carrying the value but it is having a reference to it
leader says that it is accessing a global value right so can i say it this way the rush that is
actually having a reference to i value now when it actually coming back into the call stack
already 10 times iteration has been done and the value of i is increased to 10
and it is actually checking that value of i is 10 it is outputting 10 because if you see this
functions a 10 copies will be taken put it into the web api's and when it come backs into the
call stack and it tries to refer the value of i the value of i is actually incremented by 10 times
then the then if you try to refer to that value it gets that value as a it is 10 isn't it
as you say it's a global value global scoping
guys did you get the problem here firstly what is actually happening why this is happening
how many of you understood this point okay let's see let's see this in the browser
okay let's see this in the browser let me
okay remove the debuggers here now i'll put a console on the console log i'll try to put
this one i'll try to let's say remove this i'll refresh it let's say i print this once
now if you see it here firstly if you see it here inside this local scope
inside the set timeout whenever a callback is called okay here
the value of i if i try to hover over it let's see if i try to print value of i here
here its value is already 10 the reason is that 10 loops are already iterated and when
is actually execution context is coming let me show you that actually how this thing works
console dot log
for loop iteration
okay
start
then end
okay now let me go back here try to print it
okay firstly do device let me remove this console log here
let's say i try to put it here and i call it here
no inside the console log if you see this for loop is not yet executed firstly
it is still on the line number 32 once i click a play once i click a play by the time this
callback function by the time this callback function is executed let's see what happens
okay by the time this callback function actually comes all the iterations of loop is completed
isn't it the 10 iterations of the loops is completed and this this has been actually
put down to the web i mean that callback queue and it came after out of that queue onto the call
stack again you see here onto the stack this anonymous function is there set timeout is there
it came back from that queue and by the time it came out man this loop has already iterated
and this loop has iterated once it became nine loops and when it iterates by i plus plus 10
it checks the condition okay if i'm less than only 10 then i can go inside the loop
till then i cannot go now if you see here the value of i how this is actually coming here
okay fuse uh let me show here scope
this thing
i'm having a script here one
okay this is a call stack but if i try to access here if you see the value of i becomes 11 firstly
uh i didn't print should be 10 actually
okay it kept on rotating guys if you see this uh once i hover over it the for loop
is kept on happening so if i come come out here again i try to do it again it will come out 18
but when actually console log is been registered the loop is actually happening and it is actually
does not remember if you see whatever value now let's say when what i mean to say is that
when the loop actually starts it the variable is not private to each iteration
it's it it is not private to its iteration each iteration specifically but whenever you actually
start executing this start executing after one second two second three second now whatever
value after three four seconds whatever value of i is available it will take it in but we are not
sending that surely that hey you should be taking one two three four values is this clear guys why
this is actually happening firstly that hey you are there outside you came back and if you say
that give me your coupon it doesn't work that way okay you when you come back here you will be
served whatever is available i hope this point is clear like how this works is let's say if i have
this other code console log of loop iteration start and end this part of code is execution is
completed right if you see this execution is already completed now this person let's say there is
someone 10 people standing in the line and other people they also stand in line but while they are
standing in line they get some work like async work they go out of line and all the other people who
are standing in line their work is done now when the person who left the line he comes back can he
get executed along with this people itself this people work is already done right when he comes
back he'll stand in the new queue which is the i 10th number or 11th number isn't it
so guys are you able to relate this okay now here also problem is with respect to variables itself
like they are actually global we are not binding this way now to fix this one also to make it more
private such that you actually pass a variable inside this you can actually how you can do it
using again closures how can you do it closure what was the definition of closure
what was the definition of closure that a closure is a combination of a function bundle together
along with the reference to the out surrounding state isn't it if i can bundle this particular
thing in a function let's say i put this in a function so i say that function a
okay let's say it's receiving some
value okay let's say it's receiving value i put it as well
okay now
and once this function is available and i call this function val a with value of i
now do you think this should work actually
no you never should do that ashwin you should never write for loops in a sink await
use case because ever it is actually are waiting stopping an execution and that's that's
that's not the right way of doing it
okay but i'll come to that part i'll explain more on that but do you guys see this here i
just applied the logic of closure i said that hey i bundled this particular set timeout with a function
and in its scope in its lexical scope the value of i is available now the value of i each time
let's say as you see as i say what was the use case we remember that hey this is a synchronous
use case like this line is synchronous then this line is also synchronous inside this function is
asynchronous doesn't matter set timeout is working in a scene doesn't matter but this step is
synchronous isn't it it goes inside this function and it remembers this value val
because it is actually here this function is forming a closure is forming a closure with this
right this line will also execute it simultaneously so we are each iteration whenever the
10 iterations you are doing each time you are calling this function the sink and you're passing
this value as we say that closure is some someone who remembers the value who remembers the value
even they're executed out of the context right this this actually set timeout is being actually
taken out of context coming back later but this whenever you are forming a closure it remembers
the value where it was there it's like you've been in indian going to us also you remember india right
india all those things that's like a closure even if you are there or anywhere in the world
you still remember our culture and values ethics same way closure also it remembers its lexical
scope environment is this point here even if you execute outside firstly yes did you get this
point firstly okay let's see this firstly this is working or not let's see this is working or not
if you if you see it here firstly i am able to print zero to nine again and it is actually again
happening after this iterations itself okay i hope this point is clear it is actually happening after
all the iterations itself but now i am able to print this all the things now but let me show you
that how this closer is actually forming okay let me show you this how this is actually being formed
if i try to refresh it let's say i create counter is being called now if you see this
whenever this this actually console log is printed let's say uh i go
now whenever i come here if you see whenever i try to print a a closure is formed inside a closure
a value is there because a closure always stores it uh lexical environment scope like
if it's it stores the value whichever parameters are passed here if i print it again it remembers
the value one because in for loop somewhere we passed a value one then it remembers value two
is this clear guys how this actually is working
okay i received only two thumbs up but i need few more people let me know uh if there is someone who
don't understand it still i can unmute them we can discuss over this because this concept is uh
maybe tricky i'm not sure how much tricky it is for you to understand it but if there is someone
who don't understand it let me know i'll try to re-explain this
but if there is someone who don't understand it let me know i'll try to re-explain this
but there is an another way to solve this problem
there's another way to solve this problem this thing will be asked in interviews mostly they
ask this uh but they should be able to explain reasoning like how can you fix this using closure
okay but there is another way you can solve this problem let's say instead of where i use let
instead of where i use let
let's say i try to print i after i seconds
okay if i do this now if i go back in the browser i try to remove this if you see
i'm still printing 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 now this is working when i change type of data
type from var to let but are we forming a closure here firstly are we doing something those sort of
activities here guys please answer this are we doing this closure or any functionalities here
implementing those sort of use cases no the here the trick that thing happening is let
keyword is always a block scope in this block each time a block is created we know that each
time a block is created this will be always a separate value for let it is like 10 separate
blocks of code and for each block it will have itself like this is that's that's happening
because of temporal dates like each time it will have its own new copy
because the let and const are they are having uh like block scope inside the block scope
whenever this uh in again this iteration is installed i mean whenever you do again
iteration new iteration each time a new value will be actually available for you
this point is clear like why is this with let is actually happening the thing here which is
helping us let in order to solve this is block scope and block scope is like because whenever
you write in a code of block and if there is any variable inside that which is referring to let
or const always it will have a separate copy and its private owns copy is this clear
guys give me thumbs up thumbs down that works let me uh like if you don't understand it do let me know
i received only two people giving me thumbs up so i don't see people giving me thumbs down if i
i'll consider it as yes okay now this was a introduction examples that i wanted to do
but let me go back to something called us okay uh guys do you need a break
again only two people voting up for the break too
okay let's say six seven people good so we'll take five minutes break and come back
let's say uh timer
i think some bit i'm using your app more than you use it
chalo baise in five minutes
you
guys is everyone back
uh a few more reactions just want to know are you able to understand closest did you get the point
like uh how the closers are actually formed what is the use case of closure is actually
why we need a closer like you go across you'll see a number of closers whenever you write a call
back functions you do it a number of things like if you see even if you go and let's say if i
execute this part let me pick it up one example like filter
now if you let's say if you go for the polyfills of filter also
where have we built if you see this actually filter
uh
is forming a closure here we use something called as let here firstly let doesn't really matter but
this function is actually bundled along with its scope i mean wherever you see that there is a
funded i mean function inside a function and that inner function bundle along with the state of that
particular function right is uh combinedly is called as a closure okay in the examples we have
discussed today the counter create counter is actually forming a closer and in this use case
the a is actually forming a closer
i hope these points are clear i hope you got the gist of it will build few more examples and
understand few things on the closers okay let's say i need need your help to build few more
examples okay i'll give you the questions maybe let's try it out if you can guys can figure it out
let's say this this is a combination of something concept called as function carrying
okay let's say question one this is also asked in interviews guys let's say write a function
some such that you pass x then you pass y then you pass z
now whenever let's say if i call it as sum of one then sum of two then sum of three
when i call this my output should be six this is an expected thing now how do you think this
sort of functions can be written we have just seen one syntax uh when i try to write down this
create counter if you remember uh i've had i've called this some sort of syntax like a return
function is called again right uh whatever function is returned i'm calling that again
using second uh like syntax or braces same thing you have to do something here such a way that
this thing can be achieved like you can pass on uh different arguments how do you think that
this can be achievable how can you build such functions any ideas guys how can you do this
okay guys please come on uh try it out uh whatever things comes to your mind
let's say you do this you print six
uh anyone trying out
uh i hope everyone is available in class
there's some reactions uh if you're there in class okay because everyone is silent i don't i didn't
get it like how can we do this give me your way of understanding no worries there's no one to judge
it's just like we are learning together whatever you understand whenever we see these sort of
functions how can you do this so i'm going to show you how to do this so i'm going to show you how
arun has given an answer okay and any other answers guys
um
if you know uh this was an assignment question uh right kabe so that is what i'm trying to discuss
like how would you do this because without understanding closures you your sense of
understanding this one wouldn't be right so that's the reason why i picked it up now
because closures in a way explanation itself takes half an hour to do it in last class we
took a good amount of 18 examples where we were understanding lexical scope and how things work so
didn't have bandwidth but do you uh kabir have any idea like how can we achieve this
so
i'll take it up this first thing so as arun stated that you know there is a function
some let's say this is a function sum if you see go step by step there's a function sum
there's a passed on value let's say x then how can you call a function on a function
when it is possible when you can when you can call a function on a function
when it is actually returning something returning a new function right only then you will be able to
call guys are able to understand this when would you call a function on a function like if you see
this example you were able to call this time twice at times when function was actually returning a
function okay in the same way let's say if i try to return
a function let's say i i can name it an ominous i don't need to give a name it takes a value y
then again you have to return a function called z and you are out of this returning
x plus y plus z okay now let's see if this is working first and i'll explain
how this is working what is actually happening behind the scenes
behind the scenes
if you see i'm getting output as a six as expected but
firstly think of this thing a function bundled with another function with and along with its scope
what do you think the function y is it forming a closer with this one
guys and this function sum is forming a closure with this one
right this syntax is now how if you remember like if you remember now what just happened here let's
say what just happened if i write down in a syntax let's say const let's say there is a
sum one now you actually should have been calling like this one okay inside someone
i have received something like sum two okay sum two then you have const sum three
now here if you try to directly call console.log
sum two of three
okay sum one of two now if you see what just happened here is that first level
whenever this particular thing is returned in someone this whole thing is returned isn't it
right this whole thing is returned in someone
you know let's say i copy this i put it here in the someone
if you see this is a part of which this function function y sum now here someone actually having
function i but where this value one is stored this is actually again lexical scope now that
function that closure itself says that even if the function is executed outside its scope like this
function is being pulled out and executed somewhere else even then we say that this function if it is
a part of closure it will remember its lexical scope it will remember its states so the value
of x is still persisting whenever you are executing separately also even if i execute it this way
let's say if you see it i save this one logic and try to print it it will print two times six
so do you understand the power of closure that even if you pull up somewhere
it's like if you go into any other country if he's indian he'll follow that rituals
okay it remembers its lexical scope even if he's executed outside are you able to relate more with
this example that what closure is okay now let's say i i give you one more question let's say if
let's say if you want to implement let's say
question two
write a function
let's say someone where you pass x comma y and you pass z and then you call
it this thing also should return still if i pass one two three let's say one comma two
then pass three this should still return me six
how do you think this should be written what would be the syntax of writing this one
so pretty straightforward simple just like that we have done it i hope everyone is writing down
typing time takes i know that but typing it down type it down guys
so
muneshwara has shared a partial code i think he might have instead of shift enter he might
have missed it right uh arun can you recheck your thing a small mistake
logic
but i hope the urge is has given a right answer and muneshwara might have shared it
upendra has shared answer right guys i hope this logic is pretty simple and straightforward let's
say you have function uh someone uh you have it it accepts two values x and y
and it returns a new function
which takes up extra parameters z and it returns a new function
and this function is actually executing all the values
okay if you want to execute this thing again you have to do console.log
someone
so you pass one comma two then you pass three then you call that function
uh just let me see this
okay someone was already defined here uh let me comment this part of code
clear
now yeah we were able to print six or twice it is coming from there and here again this is also
forming a closer now if you remember this innermost function is executed separately but it doesn't
it somehow it remembers the values of x y z that is forming that is coming because of our closure
let me show you this with uh a proof when i go and execute it here let's say i comment every
thing and i try to print this logic just this logic let's say i go back here in the closures
and go to the sources of the script file
i put it here debugger and let's say that i'm here firstly it calls a function uh someone so it
calls a function uh someone so it should return this lot of piece of logic let's say now when this
returns now if you see the x value and y value is one and two and let's say what happens when it
returns now if you see it formed like someone is forming a closure someone like this part of thing
is forming a closure with this part now let's say if i open this if you see it forming a closure
with values of its external or like the states surrounding states like one and two lexical scope
then there is another closer where it is storing because we came at line number 54
the second closer is this one which is actually bundling this function an ominous function with
its values whatever there so this way uh since x y z are available in its lexical scope we are
able to access this value is this clear guys how this function is this is working
now would you be able to understand whenever you see a closure anywhere
can you understand this code if you see anywhere closure
right you would be able to understand it what what is actually happening
there might be bundling it is having a you know lexical scope values available so
those things are there you know there are generally when you go for scopes right when
you go for scopes basically you will have local scope if there is something available inside this
function okay in this thing you have only window object which is pointing to this keyword other
than that it is having a two levels of closure accesses because these are bundled inside inside
inside also it is having an access to the global this is what it is actually called as a scope
chain like from local to the closure another closure then the global like from one level
to the all external levels is this clear
yes uh what is scope chain how many types of scopes are there right now i'll show you
there is this example how this let voila thing is working let's say i try to comment this piece
i didn't debug and show this one right the difference between later and what happens here
let's say i try to put a debugger here
okay now let's say i try to put a debugger but
no if you see it here firstly inside this local scope inside the set timer callback function
there is nothing available when you're going for using a lit key but there is something like a
block scope is available this block scope is available this scope is actually providing the
value of i when you're going for let you know only let and const are block scope that is something
we read now that you can see it at real time here okay if i click it play again you will
see in the block scope the value is available is this clear guys how this is working
when i use let keyword and solve that set timeout issue like when i'm trying to print zero to nine
let's give me thumbs up if you got this point or give me thumbs down if you didn't get it
okay
good great now then there's a one more thing that let's say if i pick it up one more use case
as i paste the question completely
firstly
we have to implement a function that generates a random number between one and hundred and return
a function that checks if the guest number matches the generated number let's say what i'll say is
that i'll tell you it's like a game like what happens is like you know in my heart i'll tell
you guess a number what i'm thinking in my heart and that number will be between one and hundred
if i say that let's say i think 43 or 44 in my heart i don't say it on out but you say that it
is 20 i say that the target number i mean the your guest number is less than the expected number
some something that's hard of it now how would you implement this logic like you have to handle
three conditions if generated number
whichever generated number when i said generate number i what i thought in my heart
is greater than guest number
then opposite case and then equals case three cases
so guys can you think of it like how can you approach this question again
to pointer base but uh yeah i need anything i've been anything works like just like try to figure
out like firstly you have to run generate a random number how would you generate a random number
between one and hundred think of that thing how would you generate a random number mad
dot random into hundred okay what it would give mad dot random into hundred what it would give
what would the values are range of values
uh it it gives a decimal values right if you give a mad dot random uh it's it's it stretches from
zero to one and you are trying to multiply right uh ramya says that mad dot random multiplied by
100 plus one okay i had got answer from upendra but if i combine upendra's and ramya's answer
it would be right okay let's say i'll so as you guys guessed it that yeah math library will be
something helping us to build a random number but how many of you know the difference between mad
dot floor versus mad dot seal
give me thumbs up if you understand this difference between floor and seal
right let's say what is according to floor what will be the value of
0.4 what will be the value of 0.4 0 if i say let's say 1.3
1 right if i go for uh seal let's say 3.6
should be 4
even if i have 3.1 what should be the value of seal 4 now this this is once this is clear
now imagine if i want to generate a random number now firstly we know that mad dot random
what what is the range of this thing what it returns us
what is just if i call mad dot random what it will return us
zero to one in any values right anything 0.1 0.2 anything it can come so if we multiply by 100
we are we are we're thinking that it will be from zero to one uh like you know if if let's
say if it gets number is zero itself zero into 100 becomes zero then let's say if i keep on add one
then this issue is solved in a way
isn't it no but in order to make it better let's say mad dot floor
uh dot random this one what this will do is like this use case is just handling from let's say zero
whatever you get it in like 0.1 0.8 whatever you see that it will floor it down then it will add
up to one so all the edge cases will be handled when you actually uh take this uh floor plus one
if you have either you can do something like seal seal and remove plus one
do you guys agree with this point either use seal or if you use floor do it plus one
right let's say i have a floor and i do it plus one okay now let's say we build this function called
guess game inside this guess game
we have to return another function
okay that is what a statement is saying implement a function that generates a random number let's say
this function generates a random number now in order to generate a random number let's say i take this
i take this uh and i cut it i say that const generated number
okay now let's go through the statement again
you see implement a function that takes a generate a random number between one to hundred
now we have covered like one we are generating a number and returns a function that check
if a guest number matches now let's say if we if we need to receive a guest number let's say if
this they are passing something like guest number okay in this return function and what i have to
check like whether guest number is equal equal to generate number generated number let's see
okay if it is equal i'll say that hey return congratulations i'll say that return congratulations
but you have guessed it right if it's just a if else conditions nothing much guys
if guest number is greater than generated number
let's say i say that
try a lower number again
else return try a high number again okay let's say if you uh do a
game of call and this returns a function
let's say const game start
this particular thing stays now once you start that game start dot say you pass on 20
and try to execute then it will keep on playing the game let's have to do a console log of this
one since we are returning a statement
you see it says try a higher number we don't know which number it is if i say 40 let's say
try a higher number again 60
okay now why did i write logic this way in order to in order to keep consistent of generated
number if my generated number keep on changing each time i try to do it it will fail it isn't it
firstly did you get this why did i implement enclosure format is reason because since the
session is started the generated number will be same until i keep guessing it won't change each
time i call this right i can call again let's say console dot log game start of 80
do you guys see this low so it says that number is between 60 to 80 let's say if i try to print
down here if i try to print down
you see my number is actually 85 now even if i again call it let's say if i call it again here
okay
uh anyways that number will change when i again execute it reason behind i'm calling this function
guess again again but if i load it from separately let's say game start i'm calling it from different
place this instance this actually generate function will not be called again again
but this part of logic will be called a number of times do you guys agree with that point
that we are actually fixing one generated number and you can keep on generally playing around
let's say if i say in my heart 23 number you keep on saying that guessing it
till then i won't be changing that number
yes are you able to relate that point
okay so this is also again forming a closure this is the the reason that multiple instances
this game start that 60 whatever like multiple game start functions still sharing that same
generated number 62 the reason it is because we are still forming a closure here this
guest game is forming a closure with this function and its scope like single scope
so so this is what topic is on closures guys i this is what i have come with
and i hope you all got the zest of closes like how closures and what can be examples of closures
like let's say if you go and write down in like examples of closures
in js
built in js if you see okay they might have
multiple things okay there you have multiple things but
let me give you real time things which are actually you know forming a closure
let's say add event listener is a closure
so
there might be an answer
okay
here actually they for this issue is actually related to var key where they are actually binding
the value of i
so this is the same for loop issue classical issue
but you know all the callback function which takes in and execute the function later on mostly all
the parent functions forms a closure with those child functions because they're bundled together
and child functions surprisingly remembers all the parent elements right i mean lexical scope items
okay i hope that makes sense so guys do you want me to cover set and map now
or do you want me to cover in next class just want to know your opinion
okay
i see most two people there's few more votes if you want me to cover in next class give me thumbs
up promo says now if you want me to cover now give me thumbs down i received one
okay what if we cover one topic and one topic i leave it for the next class
would that be fine it will take 10 hardly because it's a
promote can we cover in next class itself i've received like you know
to majority of people wanted to cover in next class
okay okay so with that guys i'll start the doubt session for today let me add a bookmark
i see very low on you know energy after the closures so i hope everyone got the basic
understanding of closures now i'll go back to the doubt that earlier i have received
so kabir do you understand the answer of this thing now how this thing works
would you be able to answer this one now i hope like just that that's the reason why i told that
i'll pick it up at last once we go through the multiple use cases so that you will be able to
understand how this thing works break down part by part you'll see like what is actually returning
okay and how this is actually returning
and what will be the output for this one what do you think the output should be
okay
in this in this scope in this scope
check the value of num whether it should be initialized hoisted
it multiply by two becomes a function okay
yep kabir look at here firstly
i'm returning a function let's say now if i write let's say i write a function
sum i return x comma y and let's say i return x plus y
okay let's say i store const well equal to sum of x one comma two one comma three now
what will be stored in well the return type of value calculated isn't it
right what is a number four is a return type now here what we are returning actually
function isn't it and we have learned that you can always assign functions to variables
you can always assign functions to variables let's say you can always write this right we
always write this right we have written this multiple times
so this is the same use case where it is actually returning and you are storing in a multiply by
two and then you are passing five value into it where your x value become five and num value was
two but whenever you are trying to print result whenever you are executing this part here there
is some trick going on try to remember this let's say if i go and paste this logic
did i have anywhere open
now do you see this it received nan because you are actually multiplying
a num which is undefined value into x like if you do let's say undefined
multiplied by three you'll receive not a number because here in this scope in this scope the
where num is initialized will be hoisted with undefined value but from even but in a closure
num is available but it won't go to the closure scope because we have seen in the sequence in the
scope chain that you first check local then block then closures then global right this is the order
of the scope chain a number of closures can be in between number of things okay
so guys this is actually a you know one of the beautiful concept where you will be seeing
everywhere like you know everywhere where you want to create a private variables how we want to
actually you know encapsulate the data how things works you know i i got even one example let's say
i i got even one example let's say if you see this example i'll paste it here
now what this looks like you are trying to make an api call right you are trying to make an
api call fetch call fetch data url isn't it now this fetch data is actually a function
now this function is actually bundled inside this fetch data function so we have written this logic
earlier but we didn't know that earlier that this is actually fetch data is actually forming a closure
with this part so we have seen closures day in day out everywhere but we just didn't know it
so but but if you go anywhere if you go anywhere any youtube channel anything you will be having
this example for sure for loop this is a classical question that is asked in interviews go anywhere
you will see that for loop with var they'll ask it like try to print it what is an expected output
you have to guess it right because var is again it's not a block scope it's a global scope and by
the time the set time what comes into the call stack for loop has been iterated so many times
that it refers to the i value i value is currently updated to 10 or 11 whatever value
range is there then it prints all the times that particular value but when you go for let
it have a block scope in the chain that's how it works in order to fix with a var itself you have
to use a like closure for you should wrap it with a function and pass a value into that function simple
so in next class i'll be picking two things guys from my side so i'll explain how browser
works renders html css and js and set and map and i'll revise async js
this would be fine
yeah harish you can you can
uh did you want to share your screen let me see if i can give you an access
uh can you do one thing can you uh like let me see if i can give you an access
i just want to see that how can i give an access
uh
allow multiple hosts to share the screen uh that's fine but screen share
you
okay i'll see
how do you have actually unmuted you uh can you hear me yeah you can paste the error too
that's fine i i unmuted you apparently hi hi yes yes okay so uh i was like trying practicing
myself the canon board so in between that out of nowhere when i was running on chrome browser
so the code part is okay i checked with your codes also it is showing me some error i'll post
yeah that some json issue is there while you're trying to do it yes so so json uh pars and sting
if i wherever you are doing uh like if i if i remember in group uh let's say i have that photo
uh let me check that
here i've tested it okay uh on syntax unexpected non-white space character of the j
json at position two line one column three so you are when you are trying to parse it
json dot parse wherever you are adding can you check like whether the syntax is right
uh in uh script javascript or in in javascript itself i tried pasting your code also so still
i was getting the same error okay let's see let's say like uh if i go into canban board
code
see the my code if i try to execute it's not breaking but if i see json wherever it is set
so i am doing a stringify but your part of code is actually breaking here
okay but i have not written that much i have written only up to that color selection part
right up to that only i'll say like i'm halfway through i have not completed fully yet okay so
still uh like when i try to assess those color elements you remember like while clicking the
color the top color will be changed so while typing that one only it raised and i uh make it
like i deleted these things again the same error repeating so i tried to do it but i could not
find like what exactly it is meaning okay wherever you add json right wherever you are doing
trying to uh manipulate it i have not added any json i guess so okay you haven't added the json
point yes yes unexpected non-wide space character of the json at position two i actually have to
debug it can we connect on the google meet or maybe i can get an access to your system and check it
yes that would be fine yeah okay drop me a link after the class i will connect back
okay okay in what's up yeah yeah what drop me in what's up i'll join fine thank you yeah thank you
i'll mute you back
so guys is there any other questions but you know uh there are some articles that i keep pasting
but i'll try to put it one place i'm not sure how many of you are getting a time but guys seriously
tell me would you be joining tomorrow if i paste a live link of youtube streaming right it's like
right it's it's like we collaboratively sitting together and figuring out time
and studying together okay uh thanks maneshwara it's good for us and guys is ankit available
he's not here he's under he's having struggle uh i'll share in the
whatsapp once i start streaming because i raised permissions yesterday let me see if i got that
permission if we can do it
so i go into studio
so
okay let's say i'm creating it uh yeah kabe doubt station was started actually
guys can you check this if link is working for you
oh this is from studio i guess so this might not work but share yeah this is the link
if you can check if you can join and type in on chat if this is working we can sit together
discuss communicate work on it
i i don't see anyone yet yeah shashank is there working right so we'll we'll do it tomorrow
uh we'll find right i'll share the link in the whatsapp so where we can sit together and work
work on it okay so that we can think discuss doubts and whatever it is i can keep sharing
also if i'm like it's like people sitting together and learning is that's it nothing else
okay i'll end the stream from there
so
okay cool
chalo guys then with that uh i'll connect with harry offline uh anything else guys if anyone
else is having any concerns ping me right away uh and try to keep it uh 100% guys psp 100% and
start prepping for your mock uh for html css js as i've told you break down break down into
power pieces go for first tag it down html read it through complete it then go for css then come
for js first start from the dom level try to put your hands around how we are adding event listener
how document or query selector all is working once you do that anyways i'll cover the asynchronous
js again uh the next class uh because i have to teach that because that's a tagline of the class
plus i'll take how browser works and set time map so that we'll complete uh html css but still
there is a two months of time where i'll be covering good amount of things and we'll be
learning together guys okay
so hi i hope you got to learn today something interesting concept
i hope you liked it if you liked it please share your feedback okay
uh related to yeah me too muneshwara uh like react is liberty amazing like library to learn
but open how many how will be marks how many theory problems so i have limited knowledge on
that open there like how things works but i need few more feedback feedbacks but i'm
just prepping from all over interview point of view pendra so wherever someone who will ask me
out right like how would i prepare for mock when it is specific to html css js then we have to
prepare as per that and we will be talking over this multiple times in upcoming weeks and every
week from here and then when we will be sitting together maybe 9 to 11 30 or whatever time it is
alternate days uh let's say you pick up one topic let's say if we pick a schedule like uh do you
want me to build up a schedule so that you can revise it better easily what how how it would be
easier for you to revise it for mock interviews so let me share it uh let me share that uh give
me some time i'll work it so that you can break down the slots between one one and a half hour
right not more than that so so that you have enough time and uh it's it's not like uh i give
that uh hey one and a half hour you complete html it wouldn't work that how where do you should
start from how what you have to prepare from that things also i should uh we'll talk about that okay
let me uh i'll prepare a one readme file i'll paste it in our repo itself so let's say i create
file called as a mock one and what all things how can you break down uh how which classes you can
prep from okay i'll break down i'll give it to you okay i i would say something is like just hang on
with me believe it we'll sail it through we'll we'll get uh good off like we'll we'll learn
knowledge in a better way offers and everything is like uh like depends like when when you get
shortlisted once you get i'm i'm only worried about is that once you get your CV get shortly
said that then we should not lose that uh interview like we should be able to crack it we can fail n
number of boxes no worries even if like i i'll also help you out with marks but
practicing is more important than failing at a real time interview okay and keep it
in a way that if you apply for 10 positions five calls clear five out of five two to three that is
more than enough okay so then we have extended session for good time uh we close the session
today here i hope to see you soon everyone there tomorrow and figuring out doing uh problems uh
closing out your moving your psp percentages high i'll put a reminder such that you keep on
working whenever you have bandwidth okay uh keep closing your uh assignments and psps
thank you manesh farah so guys then good night take care thank you pendra bye bye guys
you